In this video we'll learn how to
split complex tasks into a series
of simpler subtasks
by chaining multiple
prompts together. You
might be wondering why would you
split up a task into multiple
prompts when you
could achieve it with one prompt
and chain of
thought reasoning like
we learned in the previous video.
We've already shown that language
models are very good at following
complex instructions, especially the
more advanced models
like GPT-4.
So let me explain why we
would do this with two analogies
comparing chain of
thought reasoning and
chaining multiple prompts.
The first analogy to compare the
two is the
difference between cooking
a complex meal in one go
versus cooking it in stages.
Using one long complicated
instruction can be like
trying to cook a
complex meal all at
once where you have
to manage multiple ingredients,
cooking techniques,
and timings simultaneously.
It can be challenging to keep
track of everything and ensure that
each component is cooked perfectly.
Chaining prompts on the other hand
is like cooking the meal in
stages where you focus on one
component at a time ensuring that
each part is
cooked correctly before
moving on to the next.
This approach breaks down
the complexity of the
task making it easier
to manage and reducing
the likelihood of errors.
However this approach
might be unnecessary
and over complicated for a very
simple recipe. A slightly better
analogy for the same thing is
the difference between
reading spaghetti code
with everything in one long file
and a simple modular program.
The thing that can make spaghetti
code bad and difficult to debug
is ambiguity and
complex dependencies between
different parts of the logic.
The same can be true of a complex
single step task submitted
to a language model.
Chaining prompts is
a powerful strategy when you have
a workflow where you can maintain
the state of the system at
any given point and take different
actions depending on
the current state.
And so an example of the
current state would be after you've
classified an incoming
customer query the
state would be
the classification so it's an
account question or it's a product
question.
And then based on the state
you might do something different.
Each subtask contains
only the instructions
required for a single state of
the task which makes the system
easier to manage,
makes sure the model
has all the information
it needs to carry out a task and
reduces the likelihood of
errors as I mentioned.
This approach can also
reduce in lower costs
since longer prompts with
more tokens cost more
to run and outlining
all steps might be
unnecessary in some cases.
Another benefit of this
approach is that it
is also easier to
test which steps might
be failing more often or to have a
human in the loop
at a specific step.
So to summarize because
this was a long explanation,
instead of describing
a whole complex workflow in dozens
of bullet points
or several paragraphs in one prompt
like in the previous video,
it might be better to keep
track of the state externally and
then inject relevant
instructions as needed.
And what makes a problem complex?
I think in general
a problem is complex
if there are many
different instructions and potentially
all of them could
apply to any given
situation as these are
the cases where it
could become hard for
the model to reason
about what to do. And as you build
with and interact with
these models more you'll
gain an intuition for
when to use this
strategy versus the previous.
And one additional benefit that I didn't
mention yet is that
it also allows the
model to use external
tools at certain points
of the workflow if necessary. For
example it might decide
to look something up
in a product catalog or call an API
or search a knowledge base, something
that could not be achieved
with a single prompt.
So with that let's
dive into an example.
So we're going to use the
same example as in
the previous video where
we want to answer a customer's question
about a specific product, but this
time we'll use more
products and also break
the steps down into
a number of different
prompts.
So we'll
use the same delimiter that we've been
using in the previous videos.
And let's
read through our system message.
"You will be provided
with customer service queries.
The customer service query will be
delimited with four
hashtag characters."
"Output a Python list
of objects where each
object has the following format.".
Category, which is one
of these predefined fields,
or products. And this is a
list of products that
must be found in
the allowed products below.
"Where the categories and
products must be found
in the customer service query.
If a product is mentioned,
it must be associated with the
correct category in
the allowed products list below.
If no products or categories are found,
output an empty list.".
And so now we have
our allowed list of products.
So we have the
categories and then the
products within those categories.
And our final instruction is,
"Only output the list
of objects with nothing else."
So next we have our user message.
And so this message is,
"tell me about the smarts
pro phone and the fotosnap camera,
the DSLR one.".
Also "tell me about your TVs.".
So we're asking about two
specific products and also this general
category of televisions. And
both of these products
are mentioned in the
allowed products list. And
then we have a
television section as well.
Then we format the
system message and user
message into the messages array.
And then we get
the completion from the model.
So as you can see, for our output,
we have a list of objects and each
object has category and products.
So we have the "SmartX ProPhone"
and the "Fotosnap DSLR Camera".
And then in the final object,
we actually only have
a category because we didn't
mention any specific TVs. And
so the benefit of
outputting this structured response
is that we can
then read it into a list in Python,
which is very nice. And
so let's try another example. So our
second user message is, "my router
isn't working". And if you
notice in the list, we don't actually
have any routers. And then, let's format
this correctly and
get the completion.
And so as you can see, in this case,
the output is an empty list.
And so now that we have this step
to identify the category
and products, if we find
any products and categories we want
to load some
information about those
requested products and
categories into the prompt so that
we can better answer the customer
question.
And so in our
workflow the state now
after this prompt has
run is either products
have been listed or they haven't
been listed and in that case we wouldn't
try
to look anything up because there's nothing to
look up. Also if I
were to actually build this
into a system I might
use category names, maybe something like
computers and laptops
or something to
avoid any weirdness with spaces and
special characters but
this should work
for now.
So now we want to look up some
information about the products
that the user mentioned,
so about this phone,
this camera and about
the TVs in general. And so we need
to have some kind
of product catalogue to
look up this information from.
So here we have
our product information that
I just pasted in.
So as you can see we have a
large number of products
available at our store
and all of these
products are fake and
were actually generated by GPT-4.
And so for each product we have a
couple of different fields,
we have name, category, brand,
warranty and so on. And so the
products is just a dictionary from
product name to this object that
contains the information
about the product.
Notice that each product has a category.
So remember we want
to look up information
about the products that
the user asks about, so we need
to define some helper functions to
allow us to look up product
information by product name.
So let's create a function, "get_product_by_name". We
input the name
and then we're going to return product
dictionary and we're going
to get the value
for the item with the
name as the key and
then our fallback is just
going to be none.
And so we also
want to define another
helper function to get
all of the products
for a certain category.
For example when the
user is asking about
the TVs we have we'd want to load all
of the information about
all of the different TVs. So "get_products_by_category"
input the category name
string.
And to do this we want to loop
through all of the
products in the products
dictionary and check each
one to see if the category is equal
to the input category and if so we
want to return that.
So we'll do this as follows. So
first we want to
loop through each product
and we have to
get the values because
we need to actually
access the category which
is in the value.
And then, we'll return this product if
the product category is
equal to our input category.
So let's do an example for each
of these helper functions.
So first we have a product called the
"TechPro Ultrabook". So let's
get the product information by name.
So here you can see we've
just fetched all of
the product information.
And let's do an example to get all
of the products for a category. So
let's get all of the products
in the computers and
laptops category.
So here you see we fetched all of
the products with this category.
So let's continue our example and
just to remember where
we are let's print
the user message. So the
user message was tell
me about the SmartX
ProPhone and the camera
and the TVs.
And then the initial
output from the model
from the first step was this.
And so what we also need to do
is read this output
from the model which is a string.
We need to pass that into a list
so that we can use it as input
to the helper functions
that we just wrote.
So let's
write a helper function to do this.
So we're going to use the Python
JSON module and we're going
to write a function called "read_string _to_list",
a very descriptive title
input string.
And so first we'll just check if the
input string is none.
In case something in
a previous step failed we're
just going to return nothing.
And now we're going to have a try
except block to make sure
that we catch any errors.
And so, first we replace any
single quotes with double
quotes in the input
string to make sure we can pass the
JSON, and then we're
going to use the JSON
loads function to read the
input string into the array, or
the list, and then we're going
to return this, and if
there's a decode error, we're going to print
the error and then return
none. So, let's try this with our
example.
So, we're going to get our category
and product list using the "read_string_to_list"
helper function, and apply
it to this response from the
model, and then we're going
to print this
list.
So, it should look the same,
let me run this first.
And so, as you can see, it's
just the same thing, except
now the type of this
variable is actually a list
instead of a string. So, the
whole point of what we're doing
is to get the
product information into a
list that we can add to the next
instruction to the model, which is
going to be the
instruction where we ask
it to answer the
user question. And so, to do
this, we need to put the product
information into a nice
string format that we
can add to the prompt. And so,
let's also create a helper function to
do this.
So, we're going to call it "generate_output_string",
and it's going to take
in the list of data that
we just created, so this.
And then I'm
going to copy in some code, and
then we'll walk
through what it's doing.
So, now I'm going to paste in some code
and show you an example, and
then we'll talk about what this function
is doing.
So, we're going to get the
product information from our
first user message, and so we're going
to use this helper function "generate_output_string" on
our category and
product list, which, if we remember,
was this.
And so, here we have all of the
product information for
the products that were mentioned in
the user message.
So,
we have the phone that they mentioned,
we have the camera that they mentioned,
and then we have all of the product
information for all of our TVs.
And this is information
that will be helpful
for the model to be able to answer
the user's initial question.
And if you're interested in how
this function works, I'll give
a brief overview but
you can feel free
to pause the video
and read it more
thoroughly.
So it basically just
loops through all of
the objects in this
list and first checks
if there are products. If so,
it gets the information
for each product and
then it checks if there's
a category, if there weren't any
products. So that would be for this
object for example and
then it gets all of the product information
for the products in
that category. And it
just adds them to this
string and then that's what it
returns. So at this
point we've found the relevant product information to
answer the user
question. Now it's time for the model
to actually answer the question.
So let's have our system message. So
this is the instruction. You're a
customer service assistant for a large
electronics store. Respond in
a friendly and helpful
tone with, let's say, with very concise
answers. Make sure to
ask the user relevant follow
up questions. So we want
this to be an
interactive experience for the
user.
And so just as a reminder,
this was our initial user message.
I'll just add it again.
And so now we're
going to have our messages array.
And this is the input to the model.
So let's go through this. We
have our first message, which
is the system message as usual.
We have the user message.
And then we have
this additional assistant message.
And this is the
message that contains all
of the product information
that we just looked up. And so we're
saying relevant product information, new
line, and then this product information
that we just found.
And so now the
model has the relevant
context it needs to
be able to answer this user's
question. So let's get
the final response and print it.
And we're hoping that the model
is going to use
relevant information from the
product information in order
to answer the user
in a helpful way.
So first it tells the
user about the SmartX ProPhone.
It tells the user
about the Fotosnap camera
and then talks about
the different televisions that
we have in stock and then asks a
follow-up question.
So as you can see,
by breaking this up
into a series of steps, we were able
to load information relevant to the
user query to give the model
the relevant context it needed to
answer the question effectively.
So you might be wondering why
are we selectively
loading product descriptions
into the prompt
instead of including all of them
and letting the model use the
information it needs.
And so what I mean by this is,
why didn't we just include all of
this product information in the
prompt and we wouldn't have
to bother with all of those intermediate steps
to actually look up
the product information.
There's
a couple of reasons for this.
Firstly, including all of
the product descriptions
might make the
context more confusing
for the model just as it
would for a person trying to
process a large
amount of information at once.
I will say this is
a lot less relevant for
more advanced models like GPT-4, especially
when the context is well structured
like it is in this example
and the model is smart enough
just to ignore
the information that
clearly isn't relevant. The next
reasons are more compelling. So the
second reason is that language models
have context limitations,
i.e. a fixed number
of tokens allowed as input
and output.
So if you have a large number of
products,
imagine you had a huge product catalog,
you wouldn't even be able to
fit all of the
descriptions into the context
window.
And the final reason
is that including all
of the product descriptions
could be expensive as
you pay per token
when using language models.
So by selectively loading information,
you can reduce the
cost of generating responses.
In general, determining when to
dynamically load information
into the model's context and allowing
the model to decide when it
needs more information is one of
the best ways to augment the
capabilities of these models.
And to reiterate, you should think
of a language model as a
reasoning agent that
requires the necessary
context to draw
useful conclusions and
perform useful tasks.
And so in this case, we had to give
the model the product
information and then it
was able to reason
about that product information
to create a useful
answer for the user.
And in this example,
we only added a call to a specific
function or functions to
get the product description
by product name or
to get the category
products by category name.
But the models are actually good
at deciding when to use a
variety of different tools and can
use them properly with instructions.
And this is the
idea behind ChatGPT plugins.
We tell the model what tools it has
access to and what they do,
and it chooses to use them
when it needs information from a
specific source or wants to take
some other appropriate action.
In our example, we can only look
up information by exact
product and category name match,
but there are also more advanced
techniques for information
retrieval.
One of the most
effective ways to retrieve
information is using text
embeddings. And embeddings can
be used to
implement efficient knowledge
retrieval over a large corpus to
find information related to a given
query.
One of the key
advantages of using text
embeddings is that they
enable fuzzy or semantic search,
which allows you to
find relevant information without
using the exact keywords.
So in our example, we wouldn't
necessarily need the exact
name of the product, but
we could do a more
a search with a more
general query like a mobile
phone.
We're planning to create a
comprehensive course on how
to use embeddings for
various applications soon, so
stay tuned.
And with that, let's
move on to the next video where we're going
to talk about how
to evaluate the outputs
from the language model.